Guide to the Randy Riddle Collection of Race Records and Radio Programs, 1920s-1965 RL.01090
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Radio Programs, 10 boxes
  - Christmas Seal Campaign, 1950 (Box 10)
    One 16" vinyl disc. 15 minute episode of "Thunder in the Valley," a Christmas story, with Ralph Bellamy. A drama about a doctor needing an x-ray machine to detect TB in his patients. Transferred from original National Tuberculosis Association, New York.
  - Dwight Eisenhower: The Grass Roots Boy, October 28, 1952 (Box 10)
    Two 16" lacquer discs. A half-hour dramatized biography of Dwight Eisenhower, focusing on his youth and college years, prepared for the 1952 Presidential campaign and sponsored by Youth For Eisenhower.
  - American Cancer Society Fund Drive, 1948 (Box 10)
    One 16" vinyl disc. Two quarter hour public service dramas syndicated to radio stations. "Square Moon" has a man who goes to his doctor with a sore lip that might be cancer. As he deals with what cancer means, he goes to a cancer research lab where the doctor there offers him a cigarette to calm his nerves. The other drama, "An Accounting," looks at how the Society spends its donations. Both shows look at the stigma around cancer at that time. The shows were produced at the American Broadcasting Company for the Cancer Society.
  - Aladdin Lamp with Smilin' Ed McConnell, undated (Box 10)
    Six 16" vinyl discs. Thirty-six episodes (Programs 1-36) of a five-minute syndicated show sponsored by the Aladdin Lamp company. McConnell does two songs on each show - an old number from the turn of the century updated with a peppy jazz arrangement and a hymn. In between, he makes a pitch for the lovely Aladdin brand lamps and lampshades the woman of the house can find at their local dealer.
  - March of Dimes 1953 Campaign (Box 10)
    Two 16" vinyl discs. Two programs spread over 4 sides produced as fundraisers for the 1953 March of Dimes and syndicated to local stations. "Man Against the Crippler" is a half-hour drama featuring Mercury Theater alumnus Everett Sloane. The story is an overview of the history of polio research, produced just a year before the first large-scale polio trials. The second program is "Summer Concert," a program of light concert music featuring Andre Kostelanetz and pianist Alec Templeton. Both include announcements that have tips for protecting against polio during the summer months.
  - The Mad Hatterfields, 1938-1939 (Box 11)
    Eleven 16" lacquer discs. The Mad Hatterfields is a rather obscure fifteen minute serial from the 1930s originating at WLW in Cincinnati. The program was written by Pauline Hopkins, whose other credits include radio's First Nighter and Grand Hotel and who played Meg on The Mad Hatterfields. The show was directed by Owen Vinson, later the director-producer of Let George Do It. The discs came from the collection of Marty Halperin, the vice president of the Pacific Pioneer Broadcasters.
    In this group are eight fifteen minute episodes from the series on original WLW lacquers from 1938-1939. The program was probably local on WLW and offered up on the larger Don Lee-Mutual network and ran through June 1939, based on radio listings. The program is a humorous radio soap that looks at an eccentric family that works in theater; the shows are sponsored by Nestle's Red Lion evaporated milk and Horlick's Malted Milk.
    Also in the group are three discs that were used when the producer and writer of the show attempted to reconfigure it as a half-hour weekly program and sell it to potential sponsors on one of the networks. One disc contains different versions of the theme song; the other two discs contain a half-hour sample episode with an announcer that tells about the characters, its run as a fifteen minute show, and people associated with the program, selling it to potential sponsors.
  - Behind the Scenes in Hollywood, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
    Nine 16" vinyl discs. Eighteen quarter-hour shows, syndicated, about 1944-45. Bidwell McCormick, the host of the show, was a publicity man at RKO and each show includes current "behind the scenes" news of productions at the different studios, along with segments that look at the work of technicians and interesting facts about the life of famous stars. Several of the shows mention or detail problems caused by the War with rationing and ways studios worked around it; they also detail early cast choices or announcements of productions that were later changed, so they document some of the facts around the making of famous films of this period. The only surviving shows from this series.
  - Monticello Party Line, 1938 (Box 12)
    Twenty-two 16" vinyl discs. Broadcast in 1938, this block of 43 programs is from the soap opera "Monticello Party Line", sponsored by Dr. Caldwell's Syrup Pepsin, a patent laxative. This soap opera, based around the small-town lives of Monticello, Illinois, the location where Dr. Caldwell was headquartered, ran from 1934 in syndication. The show was written by Sandra Michael, who would go on in a year or two to create the Peabody winning Against the Storm.
    The program is based around a telephone "party line," though the actual party line itself is only used as a plot device on occasion in the episodes. The stories revolve around the small problems of couples Curley and Aggie and Clem and Sara and people in the town. Often, characters participate in the show's commercials. At times, the show sounds like it was influenced by character driven comedy serials, like Vic and Sade or Lum and Abner, and, with other characters and plots, more of a traditional women's soap opera. Each year the show offered, as a mail-in premium, a recipe and household tips book, supposedly authored by Sara and Aggie, that featured photos and information on the town and characters. Two examples of these books are available in Box 13.
    The show was broadcast without interruption through program 675, broadcast March, 1938. At that point, the program went on a summer hiatus and picked up that fall where it left off a couple of months before.
    Stations typically ran the program five days per week in the morning or mid-morning soap opera block alongside shows like Just Plain Bill. The program was produced by the Cramer-Krassell Company, Milwaukee, Wisconsin. Transcriptions seen in the series were pressed by Columbia, possibly in Hollywood. The first reference to the program in the Los Angeles Times is the schedule for September 22, 1936 and the last is in 1937 - in this run, it was on four days per week. There are no references to the program on radio schedules in New York or Washington, so it probably ran on smaller market stations or perhaps regionally in the West and mid-West where Syrup Pepsin was distributed. The Broadcasting Yearbook mentions the program as late as 1939.
  - Shipping labels from Your Home Front Reporter (Box 13)
  - 2 recipe books from Monticello Party Line (Box 13)
  - Digital use copies of shows
    - Aladdin Lamp (Box 13)
    - America's Famous Fathers (Box 13)
    - American Cancer Society (Box 13)
    - Behind the Scenes in Hollywood (Box 13)
    - Billie Burke (Box 13)
    - Christmas Seal (Box 13)
    - Coke Club (Box 13)
    - Dwight Eisenhower (Box 13)
    - March of Dimes (Box 13)
    - Mad Hatterfields (Box 13)
    - Monticello Party Line, 3 CDs (Box 13)
    - Plantation Echoes (Box 13)
    - Supper Club (Box 13)
    - Uncle Remus (Box 13)
    - Your Home Front Reporter (Box 13)
  - Digital master copies of shows (CLOSED) (Box 13)